James Higginson MA(Cantab) MB BChir BDS MRCSEd

Email: j.higginson19@imperial.ac.uk url: https://www.higginsonsurgical.com

Current position

NIHR Clinical Doctoral Fellow, Department of Surgery and Cancer, Imperial College London

Memberships and Registration

Membership	Number
General Medical Council	7016858
General Dental Council	258556
Medical Protection Society	376166
British Association of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgeons	2682
European Head and Neck Society	2869
British Association of Head and Neck Oncologists	924
European Association of Craniomaxillofacial Surgeons	6883

Grants, Awards and Honours

NIHR Clinical Doctoral Fellowship—£480,000 awarded as a personal fellowship to deliver a feasibility study to integrate ambient mass spectrometry with transoral robotic surgery for recurrent head and neck squamous cell carcinom, in assocition with Imperial College London and the Royal Marsden Hospital.

BAOMS Research Grant—£9,500 awarded for consumables to support my research in intraoperative ambient mass spectrometry for head and neck squamous cell carcinoma margin detection.

BAOMS Research Grant—£10,000 awarded for research into lipidomics of head and neck squamous cell carcinoma, in collaboration with the Institute of Head and Neck Cancer Studies and Education and the Phenome Centre Birmingham.

Distinction Year 2 BDS—Awarded for excellence in examinations related to craniofacial biology and development.

Qualifications

2020

2018

2012

BDS, Newcastle University.

MRCSEd, Royal College of Surgeons of Edinburgh. 2010

MB BChir, Cambridge Clinical School. 2005-2008

BA(Hons), later MA(Cantab), Fitzwilliam College Cambridge. 2002-2005

Appointments Held

ACADEMIC AND MANAGEMENT APPOINTMENTS

Deputy Lead, British Association of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgeons (BAOMS)

Reconstruction Subspecialty Interest Group.

Clinical PhD Candidate, Imperial College London.

Trainee member, National Cancer Research Institute (NCRI) Head and Neck Re-2019-

search Group.

Trainee member, NCRI Head and Neck Surgery and Localised Therapies Sub-2019-

group.

NIHR Academic Clinical Fellow, Institute of Head and Neck Studies and Educa-2016-2019

tion (InHANSE), University of Birmingham.

Director, OpenOdontoHub, A Community Interest Company supported by NHS 2015-2019

England for the development of open-source electronic dental health record soft-

Junior Trainee & Members Representative, BAOMS Council. 2015-2016

President, BAOMS Junior Trainee Group. 2014-2015

Journal Club Section Editor, Face Mouth and Jaw Surgery, providing educational 2013-15

analyses of papers for the international trainee journal of OMFS until its closure.

Treasurer, BAOMS Junior Trainee Group. 2013-2014

Treasurer, Sunderland Royal Hospital Doctors' Mess. 2009-2010

CLINICAL APPOINTMENTS

Clinical Doctoral Fellow, Royal Marsden Hospital, London. 2020-Clinical Doctoral Fellow, Queen Victoria Hospital, East Grinstead. 2019-OMFS Specialty Trainee, University Hospitals Birmingham. 2018-2019 OMFS Specialty Trainee, Worcester Royal Hospital. 2017-2018 OMFS Specialty Trainee, University Hospitals Birmingham. 2016-2017 OMFS Trust Doctor, Sunderland Royal Hospital. 2015-2016 Emergency Medicine Staff Grade, South Tyneside District Hospital.

2011-2015

Core Surgical Trainee, Hull & East Yorkshire Hospitals. 2010-2011 Foundation Trainee, Sunderland Royal Hospital. 2008-2010

Research Experience

I have peer reviewed for BMJ Case Reports and the British Journal of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery

CLINICAL RESEARCH

LABORATORY RESEARCH

RESEARCH SKILLS

Publications

As of November 10, 2020, I have had 7 full manuscripts, 4 short articles, a book chapter and 11 abstracts published.

FULL MANUSCRIPTS

Higginson, J., Breik, O., Goodrum, H. et al. Tumefactive fibroinflammatory lesion of the maxilla: Successful resection and microvascular reconstruction after failed medical therapy. Oral Maxillofac Surg. doihttps://doi.org/10.1007/s10006-020-00914-y

> Mustafa, A.M., Day, S., Higginson, J., Sharp, I. 'Determinants of Lost Theatre Capacity'. British Journal of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery. doi:10.1016/j.bjoms.2020.07.034

Chouhan, R., Higginson, J. and Martin, T. 'Confidential Image Transfer: An Ethico-Legal Dilemma'. British Journal of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery 58, no. 4 (May 2020): 478-80.

doi:10.1016/j.bjoms.2020.02.013.

Borsetto, D., Higginson, J. (Joint first authors), Aslam, A., Al-Qamachi, L., Dhanda, J., Marioni, G., Franchella, S., et al. 'Factors Affecting Prognosis in Locoregional Recurrence of Oral Squamous Cell Carcinoma'. Journal of Oral Pathology & Medicine 48, no. 3 (March 2019): 206-13. doi:10.1111/jop.12815.

Higginson, J.A., Bartram, A.C., Banks, R.J. and Keith, D.J.W., 'Condylar Hyperplasia: Current Thinking'. British Journal of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery 56, no. 8 (October 2018): 655–62.

doi:10.1016/j.bjoms.2018.07.017.

Zavattini, A., Mancini, M., Higginson, J., Foschi, F., Pasquantonio, G. and Mangani, F., 'Micro-Computed Tomography Evaluation of Microleakage of Class II Composite Restorations: An in Vitro Study'. European Journal of Dentistry 12, no. 03 (July 2018): 369-74. doi:10.4103/ejd.ejd_28_18.

Acknowledged for statistical analysis—Banks, J., Adams, S, Laughlan, K., Allgar, V., Miller, G., Jayagopal, V., Gale, R., Sedman, P. and Leveson, S., 'Roux-En-Y Gastric Bypass Could Slow Progression of Retinopathy in Type 2 Diabetes: A Pilot Study'. Obesity Surgery 25, no. 5 (May 2015): 777-81. doi:10.1007/s11695-014-1476-7.

Nyhsen, C.M., Lawson, C. and Higginson, J., 'Radiology Teaching for Junior Doctors: Their Expectations, Preferences and Suggestions for Improvement'. Insights into Imaging 2, no. 3 (June 2011): 261–66.

doi:10.1007/s13244-010-0052-5.

3

2020

2020

2020

2019

2018

2018

2015

2011

LETTERS, CASE REPORTS & TECHNICAL NOTES

2020

Lwazi, S., Wates, E. and Higginson, J., 'Bony Cystic Lesion with Associated Submandibular Lymphadenopathy on a Background of Breast Carcinoma: An Unexpected Case of Cervicofacial Actinomycosis'. BMJ Case Reports 13, no. 4 (April 2020): e232850.

doi:10.1136/bcr-2019-232850.

2018

Higginson, J., McMillan, K., Mustafa, E.M. and Grew, N., 'Use of the Superficial Inferior Epigastric Vein as an Unusual Interpositional Vein Graft'. British Journal of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery 56, no. 8 (October 2018): 761-62. doi:10.1016/j.bjoms.2018.07.001.

2018

Wates, E., Higginson, J., Kichenaradjou, A. and McVeigh, K., 'A Severe Deep Neck Odontogenic Infection Not Prioritised by the Emergency Department Triage System and National Early Warning Score'. BMJ Case Reports, 7 May 2018, bcr-2018-224634.

doi:10.1136/bcr-2018-224634.

2016

Higginson, J., Nugent, M., and Robinson, C.M., 'Should We Test for High-Risk Human Papilloma Virus in Patients with Oral Dysplasia?' British Journal of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery 54, no. 5 (June 2016): 590-91.

doi:10.1016/j.bjoms.2016.04.016.

BOOK CHAPTERS

2018

Higginson J., Praveen P., Martin T., Parmar S. (2018) 'Reconstruction in the Oral Cavity: When and How.' In: Vermorken J., Budach V., Leemans C., Machiels J.P., Nicolai P., O'Sullivan B. (eds) Critical Issues in Head and Neck Oncology. (2018) Springer, Cham.

doi:10.1007/978-3-319-98854-2_7

Published Abstracts

2019

Payne, K., Higginson, J., McCaul, J., Sharma, N., Mehanna, H. and Nankivell, P., 'Prognostic Biomarkers in Oral Epithelial Dysplasia: A Systematic Review'. British Journal of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery 57, no. 10 (December 2019): e58–59. doi:10.1016/j.bjoms.2019.10.169

2019

Higginson, J., Mawji, S., Dattani, A., Barnard, N. and McVeigh, K., 'Malignant Melanoma of the Head and Neck: Does Subsite of Origin Affect Prognosis?' British Journal of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery 57, no. 10 (December 2019): e100. doi:10.1016/j.bjoms.2019.10.290.

2019

Ali, M., Mustafa, E.M., Higginson, J. and Sharp, I., 'Operative Procedure Code (OPCS) Consistency and Its Implication on Theatre Efficiency at the Queen Elizabeth Hospital, Birmingham'. British Journal of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery 57, no. 10 (December 2019): e6-7.

doi:10.1016/j.bjoms.2019.10.009.

2019

Wates, E., Ria, B., Samara, E. and Higginson, J., 'Urgent Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery in the Pregnant Patient: A Review of the Literature'. International Journal

doi:10.1016/j.ijom.2019.03.214. Wates, E., Tan, S., Higginson, J. and McVeigh, K., 'An Incomplete DNACPR 2019 Form for a Palliative Head and Neck Oncology 25-Year-Old: Was It Valid?' International Journal of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery 48 (May 2019): 85. doi:10.1016/j.ijom.2019.03.258.

of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery 48 (May 2019): 70.

Jones, F., **Higginson, J.** and Mattine, S., 'Clinical Photography: Are We Obtaining Appropriate Consent?' British Journal of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery 56, no. 10 (December 2018): e4-5.

doi:10.1016/j.bjoms.2018.10.017.

2018

2018

2017

2017

2017

2016

2012

2020

2019

2019

2019

Mawji, S., Higginson, J., Chaggar, J., Venkatasami, M. and Green, J., 'Orthognathic Surgery: A Bibliometric Analysis of the Evidence Base'. British Journal of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery 56, no. 10 (December 2018): e45. doi:10.1016/j.bjoms.2018.10.134.

Chouhan, R., Higginson, J., and Martin, T., 'Confidential Image Transfer: An Ethico-Legal Dilemma'. British Journal of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery 55, no. 10 (December 2017): e65.

doi:10.1016/j.bjoms.2017.08.304.

Higginson, J., Chowlia, H., Martin, T., Praveen, P. and Parmar, S., 'The Use of Interpositional Vein Grafts for Free Flap Reconstruction in a Tertiary Head and Neck Unit'. Head & Neck 39, no. SI (May 2017): E71. doi:10.1002/hed.24820.

Virdi, M, Higginson, J., Praveen, P., Martin, T. and Parmar, S., 'Are Fascia-Only ALT Flaps More Likely To Develop Donor Site Seroma?' Head & Neck 39, no. Si (May 2017): E159-60. doi:10.1002/hed.24820.

Higginson, J., Bartram, A. and Nugent, M., 'Cutting It Fine: A Re-Audit of Surgical Resection Margins And Timing of Pathology Reports'. British Journal of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery 54, no. 10 (December 2016): e76-77. doi:10.1016/j.bjoms.2016.11.036.

Higginson, J., Gunasekaran, S. and Jose, J., 'Day Case Septoplasty: Ensuring Quality within Our Teaching Hospital'. International Journal of Surgery 10, no. 8 (2012): S33.

doi:10.1016/j.ijsu.2012.06.174.

Conferences and Courses Attended

Good Clinical Practice—Most recently completed 10th November 2020 2020 Data Analysis for Metabolic Profiling, Imperial College London.

EHNS Head and Neck Robotic Surgery Symposium, Royal College of Physicians, London.

Restoration of Dental Implants, BioHorizons at Houston Dental Centre, Westonsuper-Mare.

Advanced Placement of Implants, BioHorizons at Houston Dental Centre, Westonsuper-Mare.

2019	BAOMS Annual Scientific Meeting, Birmingham.
2019	BAHNO Annual Scientific Meeting, Royal College of Physicians, London.
2019	Fellows in Training Conference, Sheffield.
2019	Placement of Implants Course, Sheffield.
2018	EACMFS Biennial Congress, Munich.
2017	Non-technical skills for surgeons, Royal College of Surgeons of Edinburgh.
2017	Head and Neck Dissection Course, Keele University.
2017	Microvascular Skills Workshop, The Griffin Institute, Northwick Park Hospital.
2017	Laser Core of Knowledge, Liverpool University.
2017	BAOMS Annual Scientific Meeting, Birmingham.
2017	IAOO Congress, Bangalore.
2017	BAHNO Annual Scientific Meeting, Royal College of Physicians, London.
2016	EACMFS Biennial Congress, London.
2016	BAOMS Annual Scientific Meeting, Brighton.
2016	BAOMS JTG Conference, Glasgow (Organised and attended).
2015	BAOMS Annual Scientific Meeting, Liverpool.
2015	BAOMS JTG Conference, Newcastle upon Tyne (Organised and attended).
2014	ATLS reverification, Cambridge.
2013	BAOMS JTG Conference, London.
2012	BAOMS Annual Scientific Meeting, Edinburgh.
2012	BAOMS JTG Conference, Edinburgh.
2012	ASiT Conference, Cardiff.
2012	Art in Surgery workshop, Cardiff.
2010	BAOMS JTG Conference, York.
2010	ALS, Sunderland.
2009	ATLS, Sunderland.
	Audit

Oral Surgery—submitted for presentation at BAOS 2018

Audit of compliance with documentation of consent for clinical photography in patients undergoing surgery for head and neck cancer, presented at BAOMS 2018

Auditing speech and swallowing outcomes after major head and neck cancer treatment

Re-audit of information governance in clinical images, Presented at BAOMS 2017

Audit of information governance in clinical images, Presented at Pan-Birmingham OMFS audit meeting 2017

Complications in day-case septoplasty, Presented at ASIT conference 2012

Teaching

2018

2020, Lecture—BSc Surgical Technology, Imperial College London Delivered an online lecture on the role of ambient mass spectrometry in oral and maxillofacial/head and neck cancer surgery, to intercalating medical students under-

Re-audit of compliance with WHO peri-operative checklists in department-based

taking a BSc in surgical technology.

- **2018, Examiner—MBChB Finals** Examiner on the practical station in the OSCE for finals, May 2018. Attended training and orientation, and shadowed an experienced examiner before taking charge of the station.
- 2017, Seminar—Written Professional Communication Final Year MBChB Component, Birmingham Medical School, Dec 2017, Tutor/Assessor, leading small group teaching sessions for final year medical students, enabling and ultimately assessing their ability to write comprehensively and concisely for referrals and discharges.
- 2017, Exam Setting—Human Diseases BDS Human Disease Examination, Birmingham School of Dentistry, Aug 2017, Examiner, Attended a meeting to develop new questions for the dental student Human Diseases examination. Recieved training in MCQ setting and the Angoff process. Contributed numerous questions for use in the exam.
- 2016–2019, Lecturer—Tumour Growth, Management & Prognosis Fourth Year BDS Lecture at Birmingham School of Dentistry, lecturing fourth year dental students on aspects of oncology, with a focus on head and neck cancer. Lecture delivered annually from 2016
- **2016-2019, Careers Adviser—West Midlands Dental Deanery** Regular speaker at careers days, advising trainees on the pathway to oral and maxillofacial surgery.

Quality Improvement Projects

2019

2019

2017

2015

Following concerns about theatre utilisation, performed a service evaluation identifying the causes of lost theatre capacity. In collaboration with the quality improvement team at Queen Elizabeth Hospital Birmingham, we identified that late starts were uncommon, but early finishes and prolonged patient transport times were key determinants of lost capacity. These findings were published in August 2020 (See 'Publications', page 3, and provided both a benchmark for transport time to allow future audit, and also a clear definition of the terms *efficiency* and *productivity* in the context of theatre capacity.

Worked with Colleagues, Divisional Management and Trust IT to deliver an electronic referrals system ('Norse') to reduce interruptions for junior staff and time spent on the phone for referring clinicians.

Identified that dentally-qualified medical students working at Worcestershire hospitals were struggling to be present for the start of medical school after night shifts. Worked with the clinical director, clinical lead and HR to adjust the shift pattern to 0700–1900, allowing these vital team members to handover and attend their medical school commitments more easily.

Contributed to the East Grinstead Consent Collaborative—Identifying variance in practice when consenting for major head and neck procedures, and recommending changes to standardise practiceacross the UK.

Leadership and Management

2015-2018

Director of 'OpenOdontoHub', a Community Interest Company supported by NHS England for the development of open-source electronic dental health record software.

References

Mr Jag Dhanda

Consultant Head and Neck Surgeon Queen Victoria Hospital NHS Foundation Trust Holtye Road East Grinstead RH19 3DZ

 $\verb|jagtar.dhanda@nhs.net|\\$

Dr Lauren Ford

Post-Doctoral Researcher Department of Surgery and Cancer Imperial College London St Mary's Hospital Praed Street W2 1NY

1.ford@imperial.ac.uk